<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An other meditatio[n] of the same Hieronimus Sauanorola vpon the lxxx Psalme of Dauid</title>
            <author>Savonarola, Girolamo, 1452-1498.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11551</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21799.2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2309</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23259562</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23259562</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26464</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11551)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26464)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1803:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An other meditatio[n] of the same Hieronimus Sauanorola vpon the lxxx Psalme of Dauid</title>
                  <author>Savonarola, Girolamo, 1452-1498.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[58] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>E. van der Erve,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Emden :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1555?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁸ D⁶ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXX --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26464:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26464:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN OTHER meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me</hi> Hieronimus Sauanorola, vpon the .lxxx. Pſalme of Dauid. Qui regis Iſrael, intende.</head>
            <q>Thou that haſte Iſrael in thy gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, thou that leadeſt Ioſeph as he were a ſhepe, haue regarde vnto vs.</q>
            <p>FOr as muche as we knowe thee, Lorde, by workes brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to paſſe thorowe thy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer: then do we ſay that thou art bente to diſpoſe and ordre thinges, when as thou doſte brynge them to their ful ende and parfytnes. Contrarywyſe yf thou ſuffereſt them to fall from their parfyt ende, then do we playnly pronounce that thy gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nement is withdrawen.</p>
            <p>Conſideryng therfore howe that all the worlde is (as touchynge true &amp; ghoſtly worſhipping of thee) in great daunger, both bycauſe the moſte parte
<pb facs="tcp:26464:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:26464:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26464:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>lyeth in darcknes of myſtruſt or infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie, or alſo bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faythful forte is almoſt holly corrupted: ſo that now a dayes this maye be truely ſpoken. They haue al ſwarued out of the right waye, they are all become vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, none there is that doth good, no not ſo muche as one: Flee to thee for ſo cour, not doutyng, but maruelynge, &amp; humbly beſechyng that thou wilt not be lyke as men whych when they are earneſtly ſet on thinges that they loue wel, they take no hede or very lytle vp on other whome they haue not in ſo great ſtore. Thou therfore, O Lorde, whiche arte ruler of Iſrael, that is to ſaye, of them that beholdeth the in lyfe euerlaſtyng, to whoſe gouernaunce thou ſemeſt muche to gyue thy ſelfe: take alſo regarde vnto oure ayde and mayntenaunce. For in that heauenly region where as thy blyſfull ſayntes doth ſe thee after a maruelous ordre &amp; excedynge glorie of the inhabitaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, it appeareth vnto them as yf thou were ſo occupied in preſeruynge and kepynge them: that thou myghte be thought to haue vtterly forgotten vs, amongeſt whome all thynges are troubled, confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, and putte out of
<pb facs="tcp:26464:3"/>ryght ordre. For whiche cauſe we her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telye praye thee, that haſte dominion ouer heauen and earth in quyetneſſe: do not ſo attende onely to the bleſſed company there aboue, that thou wilt leaue dyſamayde and comfortleſſe thy faythfull aſſembly here beneth.</p>
            <p>Wherfore haue regarde vnto oure helpe and furtheraunce, O Lorde, that haſte Iſrael in thy gouernaunce: haue regarde, good Lorde, that leadeſt Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph euen lyke as a ſhepe is ledde.</p>
            <p>For by Ioſeph whiche betokeneth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, what is mente but thy fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and deuoute people? Albeit a yonge forte of people, whome thou begotte in thyne olde age, that is, in thys oure laſte and unfortunable ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: whych abydeth haynous perſew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges and reuengynges of hys bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne, and is nyrnamed of them a dreamer. Thys Ioſeph as he grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from day to daye in more greuous combrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and trouble, ſo doeſt thou leade hym thorough fyre and water, euen as a meke or gentle ſhepe vnto the ſhambles beyng continuallye ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med &amp; brought lowe: ſo that by fetters and priſons he maye paſſe forth vnto
<pb facs="tcp:26464:4"/>that kyngdome, and thoſe paſtures whiche are freſhe and floryſhyng for euer and euer. Wherupon thou that in theſe wyſe leadeſt lyke a ſhepe Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, arte myſdemed of the vnfaythful to paſſe nothynge of oure matters: and therfore be preſent, Lorde, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to reliefe and defende vs, that the wycked ianglers mouthes maye be ſtopped. For we do not craue golde, nor ryches, nor yet prontotions of this worlde: but we couet thy lyght, we earneſtly deſyre to knowe thee.</p>
            <q>Thou that ſytteſt vpon Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bim, be opened and ſette be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of Ephraim, Beniamin, and Manaſſe.</q>
            <p>Therubim betokeneth plenteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of knowledge, Ephraim bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge for the frute, Beniamin the ſonne of thy ryghte hande, Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe forgytfulneſſe. Thou therfore that ſytteſt and arte at reſte in thy ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eche worke that thou haſte ordeyned, and arte faſtened in the ſeate of thy
<pb facs="tcp:26464:4"/>euerlaſtynge manſyon, and doeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the heyghte of thy Maieſties trone: as the Kynge, as the Lorde, as the Iudge and mayſter of all: thou (I ſaye) that ſytteſt vpon Therubim, that is, vpon the plenteouſnes of knowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, farre ſurmountynge and paſſyng all knowledge and all vnderſtanding, for that thou arte vndoutedly a ſecrete God and vnſearcheable: be opened and appeare (I beſeche thee hartelye) vnto Ephraim, that is to ſaye, vnto thy people whyche nowe bryngeth for the frute to thy honoure, ſo that they maye knowe the fully and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectlye. For who ſo knoweth thee: he loueth thee, he forgetteth his owne ſelfe, he loueth thee better then hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and dothe wonderfully profyte the congregacion. Be reueyled alſo afore Beniamin, that is, afore all thy choſen and marked forte abydynge here, or elles where, whyche no doute euen for thy verye choyſe and appoyntement are made worthye to be called the chyldren of thy ryghte hande: ſo that thy people maye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and that thy chyldreu ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed abrode maye comme together, and
<pb facs="tcp:26464:5"/>that there maye be one ſhepe houſe and one ſhepeherde.</p>
            <p>Open thy ſelfe alſo to Manaſſe, to all the Infidelles, whome thou ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt to haue caſte out of remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, bycauſe they haue forgotten thee, for ſo muche as thou haſte ſo longe wythdrawen from them the foode of lyfe. Shewe thy ſelfe at the laſte vnto all the worlde, that menne may comme out of darkenes and the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of deathe into lyghte, and maye ſette ſtrayghte theyr ſteppes into the waye of peace. But yf the ſtubbourne ſecte wyll vnnethes be amended, and yf the nombre of thoſe fooles be excedyng great.</p>
            <q>Rayſe vp thy power, and come, that thou mayeſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vs ſafe.</q>
            <p>Lo, the ryche oppreſſeth the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, the rulers deſpoyleth the ſymple flocke, the vngodlye perſeweth the ryghteous wythout anye petie: thy faythfull fyndeth fewe fatherlye hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
<pb facs="tcp:26464:5"/>they haue no maynteyners.</p>
            <p>Full manye a one (alaſſe) is drawne to hell, thorough the euell enſamples of prieſtes and the cleargye, whyche is cleane wythout hope of recouerye towarde amendement. There are a paſſynge meany of noyſome Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeis, a great rable of harmefull hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, wyth whoſe poyſoned exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions and leſſons the whole worlde is infected. They wyll not heare the wordes of trouthe, no man maye cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them: wherby thy faythfull dare not ones lyfte vp theyr heade.</p>
            <p>What doeſt thou, O Lorde? Why ſleapeſt thou? Wherfore doeſt thou wytholde thy myght? Styrre vp thy power, I humblye beſeche thee, and comme. Thou that arte euery where, wyth thy ſcourges and wyth thy ſtrength ſtryke theſe falſe and myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuous deprauers of thy worde, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye theſe craftye and malicious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers of thy ſeruauntes, condempne theſe obſtinate and deuelyſhe deſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of thy grace. I do not ſaye thys, I do not wyſhe it, I do not aſke thys, as and I were delyted to ſe them punyſhed: but that thou maye ſaue
<pb facs="tcp:26464:6"/>vs thyne elected and choſen, ſeruyng thee continually, louynge thee aboue all theſe thynges, euermore obeynge thy decrees and commaundementes. Thou aunſwereſt me perchaunce in thys wyſe. Yt I ſhall caſte in my ſwearde of vengeaunce, yf I ſhall ſende peſtilence amonge them, yf I ſhall pyne them wyth honger: thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou then, that thou thy ſelfe canſt continue in ſo muche and ſo greuous trouble?</p>
            <q>O good God do thou turne vs, and ſhewe vs thy face, and we ſhal then be in ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde.</q>
            <p>For why, we are frayle and feble, nor we truſte not in oure owne vertue or power: for that we are not ſufficient ſo moche as to y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine any thinge of oure ſelfe, as of oure owne abylytie, but oure ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunce is of God. For thys mortall fleſhe is bourdenouſe vnto the minde, and thys earthlye dwellynge holdeth downe the witte couetynge to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plate ſondry matters. Wherfore do thou
<pb facs="tcp:26464:6"/>conuerte vs o God. Tourne vs to the fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earthly thoughtes to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, tourne vnto the our dyſſobedient &amp; rebellious wil and arbytryme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: and to vs ones tourned ſhewe thi counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we maye know the: declare thy powre, that we maye feare the: vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy wiſdome, that we maye honour the: ſhewe forthe thy goodeneſſe, that we maye loue the: ſhewe thy ſelfe ones ſhewe thy ſelue agayne, ſheue thy ſelfe contynually, that we maye paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough trouble with a gladſome chere: and ſo ſhal we be ſaffe. For if thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vs, we ſhal be in ſauegarde: if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> takeſt awaye thy hande, we can not be ſaued. Why taryeſt thou Lorde? Why doſte thou not fauourably heare my requeſt?</p>
            <q>Lord God of myght, how long art thou angrye wyth thy ſeruante pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng vnto the.</q>
            <p>Ful ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue I aſked the, ryght lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge haue I deſyred the, many a tyme ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue I beſeched the. Wherfore the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doſte thou not lyſten vnto me gracyouſly? Wherfore doſt thou make ſuche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laye? Why? arte thou yet to dyſpleaſed?
<pb facs="tcp:26464:7"/>Wyth me for my ſynnes? If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doeſt at counte &amp; reken my fautes Lorde, Lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de who ſhal be able to abyde the? Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore o Lorde that haſte power to do al thynges, o God that ruleſt all thynges vnto whom they which vpholdeth the worlde done obeyſaunce, whome high poures, whome the heuens &amp; theyr do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s do reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly feare: Lorde God of myght, how longe wilte thou be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grye with thy ſeruaunt prayeng vnto thee? where is thy entyre loue? Where is thi ſtrength? Where is thy manifol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de mercye? What? Ar they refrayned &amp; kepte awaye ouer vs? We wil crie vnto the both nyght &amp; daye, knowing verely that if ſo be thou wilte make a cariaunce, yet wol thou at the laſte ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylly heare our importunate ſute.</p>
            <q>Thou ſhalt feede vs with breade of teares, &amp; ſhalte gyue vs drinke of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res by meaſure.</q>
            <p>I hope (I ſaye) that I ſhal be herde, for that thou haſte euermore loued trouth. Denye thy ſelfe thou canſt not. For thou haſte promyſed: Aſke, &amp; it ſhal be gyuen ye: ſeke, &amp; ye ſhal fynde: knock &amp; it ſhal be opened vnto you. Albeit fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte
<pb facs="tcp:26464:7"/>thou ſhalt fede vs with breade of teares, with bitter breade, with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt breade. For teares ar both ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, &amp; ſwete. Sowre, for the abſence of goodneſſe: ſwete, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> certaynte of fyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng out goodneſſe. Bytter they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, for bycauſe that truſte whyche is dryuen of &amp; delayed greueth the poore ſoule: pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te they ar, for the preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of thi ſweteneſſe, which ſtirreſt vs vp to praye, &amp; cauſeſt vs to cal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnſpeakable ſighes. And thou ſalt gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue vs drynke of the cuppe that is in thi hande ful of the ſweteneſſe of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re wyne. For why, thy comforting ſhal reuiue our ſpyrites &amp; quicken our myndes, euen according to the heape of the greafes &amp; anguyues in our hert Drynk therfore ſhalt thou gyue vs in the teares of troubles, which waſheth the face of our conſcience, which clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rith our vnderſtanding, which moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtureth our herte with deuotion, &amp; yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs the ſauour of loue &amp; charyte. Than thy good teares ar ſwete tears Doutleſſe, which hathe bene foode to vs daye and nyght. Heare vs therfore thou ſhalt, but afore that ſhalt thou fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vs &amp; gyue vs drynk in trears: not more the we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bear, but in meaſure,
<pb facs="tcp:26464:8"/>after the lymytyng of the trouth. For thou wylte not let vs be tempted more then we can beare, but thou wilte ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke alſo this profyte to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge, that we ſhal be the better able to ſuffre. Thou ſhalte fede vs, I ſaye, with teares, not alwayes, but a certayne ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me which thou haſte putte in thine ow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne powre, Now lo, when that ſame tyme apoynted is ones comme: then ſhal our weping &amp; waylyng haue ane ende, then ſhal thy angre ceaſe, then ſhal our prayers be accepted. Thou ſhalte tourne vs to the, thou ſhalte ſhewe the lyghte of thy countenaunce, thou ſhalte rayſe thy myghte, thou ſhalt make vs ſaffe and ſounde, and thou ſhalt be reueled &amp; opened before Efraim, Beniamin, and Manaſſe: &amp; thou ſhalte enlarge thi churche, and take regarde to the gouernaunce ther of. The meane whyle, we ſhal poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de our ſoules in our ſufferaunce. For why,</p>
            <q>Thou haſte ſette vs to be with ſayed of our neyghbours, and our enemyes haue mocked vs,</q>
            <p>In the meane ſeaſon as thy chyldren
<pb facs="tcp:26464:8"/>doeſt thow chaſtyſe vs: that we maye be clenſed, that we laye not our harte vnto riches, that we folowe not worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely prayſe, that thy trouthe maye the more comme to lyght: and for theſe cauſes haſte thou ſet our neyghbours to replye &amp; ſpeake agaynſt vs. And who beene our neyghbours, but theys diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blers: whiche ar nether hotte nor colde, whiche in their outward behauy our done appere as they wer Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Lord (they wil ſay) I tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am not as the commen ſort of men ar vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryghteous, rauyſhers lecherouſe, yea euen as this Publicane is: I faſte twy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe in a weke, I gyue in almes the tenth parte of al that I haue: &amp; yet for al this, they be not inwardly true Chriſtians. They ar therfore our neyghbours, by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe they ſeme to be lyke vs in theyr works: but they ar not of our houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, bycauſe they haue not lowly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they haue not loue &amp; charyte.</p>
            <p>Why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after what facyon haſt thou ſet theſe neutralles to wythſaye and ſtryue agaynſte vs: but for bycauſe thou haſte lightened vs in the waye of trouthe, and haſte ſhewed vs thy coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. By that lyght haue we eſpied then &amp; perceyued that they be paynted
<pb facs="tcp:26464:9"/>graues which wythout appeareth ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye &amp; gorgyous, but within they be ful of deade mennes bones &amp; al vnclean<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyneſſe. Wherfore leſte ſymple folke &amp; other Chriſtyans ſhoulde peryſh, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough theyr ſayengs and enſamples: we haue toide them boldely, &amp; gyuen them this warnyng: beware of the Phariſes leuyn, which is hypocriſye or a fayned pretence of holyneſſe. Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rymonyes, cuſtomes, or vſages ſhal not ſaue yow: we haue diſcloſed &amp; play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely ſet oute to euery mans ſyghte theyr ſcrupulous conſcience. We haue reproued &amp; rebuked them, ſayeng: yow be they, that make your ſelfe parfecte &amp; ryghteous before men, but God kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth your hartes: for what ſo euer is loftye afore men, is abomynatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afore God. Hereupon ryſeth ragyng enuye, herupon groweth greate malyce he reupon ſpringeth &amp; encreaſeth debate and controuerſye. For they ſet more by mennes glorye, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Goddes glory. Therfore go they romyng vp &amp; downe the cyte, they runne hyther &amp; thyther, they hau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s howſes, they grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge at vs, they ſclaunder vs, they ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke agaynſt vs, they perſewe vs. And ſo it is comme to paſſe, that our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes
<pb facs="tcp:26464:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>hathe mocked vs. Our enemyes ar manifeſte &amp; open ſynners, the fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des &amp; louers of this world, proude, co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uetous, ryattous, curſyng, man quay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and aduerſaryes of Chriſte his croſſe. Theſe (I ſay) not willing to hear our wordes, yea rather thy wordes o lorde, but fleyng away from them per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuaded &amp; brought in to a wronge beleff by thoſe hypocrites, hath ſcorned vs, &amp; diſdaynefully deſpyſed vs, as and we wer idyoths or fooles. And what is the cauſe, that our neyghbours hath contraryed &amp; wythſayed vs, &amp; that our enemyes hath deryed vs? wherfore done our neybours more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myes? Why? Ar not the Phariſes our enemyes? yes truly they bene our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our deadly enemyes: yet ar they wyly &amp; crafty, yet ar they ſecrete &amp; verye cloſe. For they do bear vs in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that they be our frendes, they ſaye that they loue vs wel, they falſely pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tende that they ſpeake for the trouthe ſake, and not for hatered of vs: ſo that theſe hypocrytes hurte vs more, than open ennemyes. They ar called therfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re neyghbours, bycauſe they make them ſelfe our frendes, and yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe are mutteryng agaynſt vs.
<pb facs="tcp:26464:10"/>Wheras oure enemyes dothe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>emye laugh at vs. yea &amp; our enemyes wolde not ſcorne vs, if theſe felows wer not buſye in talking agaynſt vs. yea our enemyes myght be tourned to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, if theſe medlers did not let them. To be breue our enemyes wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de becomme our frendes, &amp; defenders of the trouthe, if thy churche had no ſuche Phariſaical wythſayers. Great is the battayl, daungerous is the ſtry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe, douteful is the vyctorie. Wherfore,</p>
            <q>Lorde God of myght, tourne vs vnto the, ſhewe vs thy countenaunce, and we ſhal be ſaffe ynough.</q>
            <p>God that gyueſt ſtrength vnto the power aboue to fyght wyth out dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de agaynſt the olde dragon, and bolde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to achiue all harde enterpriſes: God of myght tourne vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fonde loue of our ſelf vnto the parfyt loue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wherby we maye be knytte vnto the, and ſtycke to the: for ſo ſhal we be afra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yed of nothyng, but fyghte oute thy battayle wyth a full confidence. For thou art our ſtrength and our ſtaye, our ſuccoure, &amp; our defence. Therfor
<pb facs="tcp:26464:10"/>Therfore ſhewe the light of thy counte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce, ſet out thy trouthe. Make thi lyghte euident &amp; playne: that theſe hy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pocrites do not deceyue vs, that they wrappe not our hartes in darkeneſſe, that we maye auoyde &amp; eſcape theyr ſnares, &amp; maye walke in the waye of trouthe. And ſo if thou delyuer vs, if thou lyghten vs, if thou fyght for vs, we ſhal be ſaffe. Go to Lorde, do ſo Lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de: aryſe, awake, comme, &amp; tarye no le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Where be thy manyfolde mercyes ſhewed in olde tyme, Lorde? Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre thyne owne labours, do not ſet lyghte by thyne owne paynes, do not deſpyſe the workes of thyne owne handes.</p>
            <q>Thou haſte, remoued thy pineyarde out of Egypte, thou haſte caſte oute the heathen, and haſte grafted it.</q>
            <p>Thy vyneyarde is thy church. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore is it cleped a vineyard? Bicauſe it yeldeth wyne which dothe make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes myndes in a maner dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with loue of heuenly thynges, which dothe refreſh and make gladde our hartes. A good vineyarde, a vyneyarde of the beſte, that turneth into wyne what ſo
<pb facs="tcp:26464:11"/>euer is layed aboute the rote therof.</p>
            <p>If a man wil putte vnto the roote he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of water, dou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, or any other thing: it chaungeth into wyne al to gyther, what ſoeuer it be that it draweth vnto it ſelfe. For it neuer bringeth forthe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther water or dunge, or any thynge, but wyne. So al that is offered vnto the Churche, that is to ſaye, vnto the faythful ſoule of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: be it mockage, or perſecutyon, or golde, or commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or curſyng: it turneth al to chary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, to pacience, to lowlyneſſe, &amp; other vertues. This vineyarde, theſe fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful menne nothyng coueting, nothing fearing in this worlde haſte thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued out of Egypte, that is to wete, out of darkeneſſe. For they wer in lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of lyght for ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; in the dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſe of ſynne: they knewe not theyr ende, they coulde not tel whither to go. Thy lyght haſte thou ſente them, and out of darkeneſſe haſte thou broughte them. But the heathen (that is) wycked ſoules &amp; frowarde men, without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, wythout lawe, wythout lernyng did malycyouſly perſue them, and did deſtroye thy vineyard. They were eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyke ſtoones very harde ſtrykers, hur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting the fete of them that walked ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in,
<pb facs="tcp:26464:11"/>marring the braunches, &amp; vtterly letting the frute of the vineyarde.</p>
            <p>Thou haſte therfore caſte owre the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then: thou haſte kylled the bloodeſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kars &amp; murderers of thy wytneſſes: thou haſte brought to confuſyon the maumettes and idolles, thou haſte gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the deuil heretikes &amp; them that be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obſtinate in theyr owne fantaſies: thou haſte gathered the ſtones togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and caſte them for the, and made them to be farre from thy vineyarde, and they ar ſonke downe into the dep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. Thou haſte grafted it in thy holy mownte, in thy faythe, in the parfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tneſſe of thy iuſtice, in thy Chriſte. It hath paſſed thorough the redde ſee, it hath paſſed thorough fyre and water: for dyuerſe troubles hath it not gyuen ouer, it is ſaffe ynough.</p>
            <q>Thou haſte ben the guyde of the ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in her eye ſyght: thou haſte pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the rootes of her, and ſhe hath fylled the earthe.</q>
            <p>A ſtronge, a wyſe, a gentle, a great guyde. For why, God is a myghty Lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, &amp; a myghty King aboue al Kinges. Who than wolde not folowe ſuche a guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de?
<pb facs="tcp:26464:12"/>But after what maner haſte thou ben her leader? Thou haſte come dow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, thou haſte apeared in fleſh &amp; the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon of a man: for her, haſte thou ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red perſecutions, wythſayenges, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynges, ſcorninges tormentrie, yea &amp; deathe of the croſſe. To thy father did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou paſſe forthe by the waye of thy paſſion, and thou madeſt a procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: Who ſo wil comme after me, muſte denye hym ſelfe, and muſte take his croſſe, &amp; folowe me. A graunde ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitayne, a difficulte waye. But who wil be afrayed, hauing ſuch a guyde that wil not lyngar behynde a man, but go before hym? Thou therfor (o Lorde) haſte ben not a lurking capitay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, but open and manifeſte: al men myght beholde the. Guyde of her ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney haſte thou ben en her eye ſyght.</p>
            <p>For openly werte thou nayled vpon the croſſe betwyexte two theues. And bycauſe the vyneyarde is but feble, for that the vynetre it ſelf is but a weake maner of woode: thou haſte ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened it, &amp; haſte ſette the rootes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. No fleſhly man, nor aungel hath planted it: but thou with thyne han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, with thy wyſdome, with thy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, with thy bounteouſnes haſte ſette
<pb facs="tcp:26464:12"/>the rootes of her loue, of her charite, of her good affection. Thou haſte pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this vineyarde (I ſaye) in a good grounde, in the grounde of lyuing creatures, in thy woundes, in thy croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, in thy godhed: and therfore hathe it yelded frute, it hathe brought forthe pleaſaunte wyne, wyne of the beſt, ſuch wyne as wol rauiſh a mans min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de: with manifolde braunches is it en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creaſeth, ſo that it hath fylled the holle earth. It hath fylled (I ſay) the earth with vertues, wyth heuenly gyftes, with grace, lyghte, &amp; the knowledge of God. Not with the Philoſophers cun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ninge, whiche when as they knewe God, they did not eſteme him &amp; glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie hym as God, nor yet rendred than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes vnto hym: but they vaniſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayne in theyr conceytes &amp; thoughtes, theyr folyſh hartes was darkned and blynded. For they naming &amp; counting them ſelfe to be wyſe men, becamme very idyotes &amp; fooles. So is it not with thy vineyarde, o Lorde. And why? Mary,</p>
            <q>The ſhadow of it hath couered the hilles, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vynes therof hath ouerſpred the Cedre trees of God.</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:26464:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Which is the ſhadowe? The olde te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtament goyng afore the trouthe of the Goſpel, euen as our ſhadou goeth before our bodye, when the ſunne com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth after: but whan the ſunne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth before our face, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dothe not the ſhadowe go afore but commeth after, and we ſe it not. Semblably the Law (as it were a ſhadowe) went before the trouthe and grace whyche is by Ieſus Chryſt, becauſe the ſunne of ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes did then folow, that he myght af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward come, and apeare, and ſhewe his face to vs. Wherfore he came, and opened the trouthe, and ſette it before our eyes: now, lo the ſhadow foloweth and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth after our back. We ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do flee awaye from it, and do go towarde the ſunne. The ſhadowe of the Lawe, and of ſacrifyſes is ouerpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, becauſe the ſunne of ryghtouſnes Chriſte our God is come. The ſhado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we of it therfore, that is to ſaye, the La<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we &amp; the darke teaching of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes couered the mowntaynes. Who ar the mountaynes? Men ſtedfaſte in faythe, high in parfectnes of iuſtice &amp; contemplacyon of heuenly thynges. Certeſſe, the Patriarches and Prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, not the Philoſophers and Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, which ben the mountaynes of
<pb facs="tcp:26464:13"/>pryde. This vineyarde than proceded from the vnſearchable &amp; heuenly lygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of the Patriarches &amp; Prophetes.</p>
            <p>And the ſhadowe herof hath couered the hylles, that is to ſaye, Biſſhoppes, Patriarches, and prophetes: which ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing plentieth of knowlege in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we, &amp; beyng replenyſhed with ſpirit of Prophecye did couer thy vineyarde, &amp; mayntayn it. Thou diddeſt come (Lord) vnto thy tyllers of thys yard, &amp; they kil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, &amp; dyd caſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> out of it. Houbeit y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worthely deſtroye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thoſe naughty occu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyars, haſte lette forthe thy vineyarde to be hyred of other huſbandes which hathe done the frutes therof (that is to ſaye) hath turned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhadow of the Lawe into lyght. The carnal ſenſe haue they drawne vnto a ſpiritual vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, that when they be wery they might ſytte vnder the ſhadow therof, &amp; be cooled from feruent heate: yea the ſhadow of it is becomme lyghte, for that the very Lawe it ſelfe ſpiritually taken and vnderſtanded is made the Goſpel: vnder whoſe ſhadowe which is the lyghte the wery ſoule reſting thus doth ſinge and ſaye: Vnder his ſhade haue I ſyt whome I lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged for, his frute is ſwete and pleaſaunt to my throte, And agayne. The breathe of our
<pb facs="tcp:26464:14"/>mouthe, is Chriſte. The Lorde was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in our treaſpace, vnto whome we ſayde, In thy couerte ſhal we lyue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the gentiles. Then did he multi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plye the vinebraunches emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then. For the Gentiles camme to Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte, to the tyller, to the vinetre, to the vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neyarde: the braunches wer multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they did growe for the a greate nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre, and not wythout a cauſe wer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de euen as vyneyardes, and the vines therof wer lifted vp on hygh. Yea they couered the Cedre trees of God. Which ar the Cedre trees of God? Vndouted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Apoſtles, his Euangeliſtes, the teachers of his congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherfore the choſen children out of the Gentiles camme to them, they tooke them by the hande, and ſayde: Wyth you will we go, for we haue herd that God is with you. Than wer the Cedre trees gladde, they bowed downe themſelues, &amp; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de: Clyme vp, clymme vp ouer vs, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vs: for we wil heare, we wil holde you vp, we wil lyfte you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the groun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. So the Gentiles wente vp by fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, and wer buylded vpon the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the Apoſtles and Prophetes, euen Chriſte Ieſus hymſelfe being the hygh corner fronne. Theſe vines ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:26464:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath ouerſpredde the Cedre trees of God. O happie vineyarde, o bleſſed brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches, which haue not folowed the wyſdome of foliſh Philoſophers: but that heuenly ſapience of the mountay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; Cedre trees (that is) of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes &amp; Apoſtles, the lyght vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the waye of trouthe that leadeth you truely vnto your ryght countrey. But how large is this vineyarde? Is it the lande of Iewry alone? Is God onely the Iewes theyr God? Doute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe from the ſunne ryſyng vnto the ſunne ſettyng, Lorde, greate is thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me emong the people.</p>
            <q>The hathe ſtreched out her braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches euen to the ſee, her longe ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding reacheth vnto the ryuer.</q>
            <p>The Cedre trees of Libane reioyſed, they cried &amp; lyfted vp theyr voyce.</p>
            <p>Theyr ſounde went forth in to al the worlde, and theyr wordes vnto the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt borders of the whole worlde. The ſee herde, and ſwelled, &amp; the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the was troubled. The floodes of the ſee rooſe. Maruelous ar the ſurges of the ſee, maruelons is the Lorde in high places. Troubled wer the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taynes:
<pb facs="tcp:26464:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>proude princes, preſſes, ſcrybes &amp; Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes. The kinges of the earthe ſtoode by, &amp; the rulers camme to gyther a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the Lord, &amp; agaynſt his Chriſte. But God thundered from heuen, &amp; the hygheſt gaue his voyce. The voyce of the Lorde in a power, the voyce of the Lorde in a magnificence. Stones did liſten, and forthwyth trembled trees of the woodes: the harde harted &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruteful Heathens did lyſten, &amp; forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wer they turned into braunches of the vinetre. The ſee behelde, and ranne a waye, Iordane the ryuer tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned backeward agayne. But the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles euerywhere camme vnto the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, they faſtened themſelfe to it by fay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the and loue: they encreaſed greately euen to the ende of the worlde, to the mountaynes &amp; the ſee: wheras tyraun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and frowarde people wer ſtryken, caſte downe into hel, and ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med wyth the ſea. Contrarywyſe our vineyard hath ſpredde forthe her brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches euen vnto the ſee, that is, vnto the fardeſt parte of lande. The ſee therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re compaſſeth thys vineyarde, beateth vpon it, but the whaues be broken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt it.</p>
            <p>But what worthed of the countreye
<pb facs="tcp:26464:15"/>of Iewes? It was hardened, it was dryed vp, it yelded no frute. Thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte cutte of therfore ſuche braunches (o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly tyller) &amp; haſte throwne them in to the fyre. Why, ar al the brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed &amp; loſte? God for bidde. For yet the leauinges bene ſaued. Many brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches of Iewes accordyng to thy wyll and appoyntment, hath continued in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vinetre, &amp; hath yelded parfecte frute The vineyarde growed, ane ſtretched forth her vynes euen vnto the ryuer. What meaneth this, Lorde vnto the ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer? Why, is ther in al the worlde but one flode? Is the worlde ſhutte vp or encloſed by ſome ſee, or any ryuer? No veryly: but lyke as when the Prophete is named, Dauid is mente therby for his excellence, and Paule whan the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle is named: ſo in this place wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as is mencioned a ryuer generally, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand thou it of Iordane, whiche was hallowed and ſanctifyed of my ſonne: for it alone hath that preemy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nence.</p>
            <p>What meaneth then vnto the ryuer, but vnto the ryuer Iordane? That is, vnto the people of the Hebrues did ſhe ſpredde forthe her braunches. Thynke not than the people of the Hebrues to
<pb facs="tcp:26464:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26464:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26464:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>be al to gyther expelled. For that ſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne whiche they in theyr buyldyng re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, is made the hedde corner ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. Therfore bygge was the church then o Lorde, bygge (I ſaye) in worthyneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe: greate in trouthe, greate in parfecte neſſe of vertues, greate in charite, gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in the nombre of wonderful wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, large alſo in ſpreading forth, grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te it was: for bycauſe a greate Lorde arte thou that diddeſt grafte it, that diddeſt gyue it encreaſe: bycauſe thou diddeſt enlarge it, bycauſe thou (Lorde Ieſu) werte the guyde of her iourney. Thou diddeſt labour in it, thou diddeſt trauayle, thou diddeſt watche: thou did deſt conſecrate her with thine owne blode, &amp; with the bloode of thy martyrs or witneſſes. Where than ar thy pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes becomme? where is the ſweate? where is thy bloode? What haſte thou done Lorde God? what haſte thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, o my ſauyour?</p>
            <q>Wherfore haſte thou throwne downe the wal of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>inyarde? and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do euery man that paſſeth by the waye gather the grapes?</q>
            <p>Why haſte thou done this, goode Lorde? what is the effecte? The cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb facs="tcp:26464:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Aungels haſte thou put from it: they did kepe awaye theues, they did defende it. Where is that ſure war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de now a dayes? Where ar the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes? Where ar the Apoſtles? the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, the heardemen compaſſing this vineyarde, dryuing out wicked ſpyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, banyſhing heretikes, correcti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vn gracious perſones, and preſeruing the weake and vnparfecte? Which is the wal? The cuſtodye of Aungels, the defence of ſhepardes, the holy doctrine of preachers. Where is this wal? It is deſtroyd? Why, who hath pulled it downe? Thou Lorde, whiche haſte ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken awaye thy good preachers, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che haſte gathered thy ſhepardes in to heuen, whiche haſte taken awaye thy meſſengers. Wherfore haſte thou throwne downe the wal of this vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde? Haſte thou ſo done, for that ſhe maye fulfyl her naughtynes, for that her wickednes maye be accomplyſhed to the entent to punyſh her, &amp; ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe her? But what hath ſhe lefte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done? What ſynne is ther that maye not be founde in her? Verely (Lorde) lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke how that her wickednes is brought to the ful ſwynge. And now dothe eche body that goeth by the way plucke her
<pb facs="tcp:26464:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>grapes. Not the true orderers of the vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neyarde, not the true tyllars gathereth her frutes: not al good, nor yet a fewe good, nor yet ſome good and ſome euil, no not ſo muche as one good, but eueryche one that commeth by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye plucketh her grapes. None but they which kepeth not thy ordinaunce, yea whiche knoweth not the waye of God, open ſynners, of an euil reporte ar cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen vnto the miniſterie of the aulter: to thoſe ar benefices gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they do gather the frutes of the vineyarde for them ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe, and not for the: they do not regarde thy poore people: they do not fede the hungrye: they clothe not the naked, they harber not the ſtraunger: they defend not the wydow and the fatherles childe: they done eate the lambe out of the floc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, and the calfe from the middeſt of the hearde: they do ſinge after the noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of ſhaulmes &amp; organes: they ſuppoſed they hadde the inſtrumentes of ſonge euen lyke Dauid: chaunting in quiers, prayſyng God w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr lyppes, &amp; beyng farre from God in theyr harte: dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng wyne in cuppes of golde and ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, &amp; dreſſed with very ſwete &amp; ſauery oynteme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: and yet hathe no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rough puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Ioſeph, they
<pb facs="tcp:26464:18"/>take no maner pyte vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the nedy &amp; poo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re bodye. Theſe therfore that paſſeth by thy waye, gathereth vp the grapes of thy vineyarde. But what ſhal I ſaye, o Lorde? For al they alſo whiche paſſeth by theyr owne waye, doth plucke the frute of the vineyarde. For they wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by theyr owne waye, &amp; ſeyng the wal of the vineyarde deſtroyed, hath ouerpaſſed theyr waye. They made not a ſtreyght iourney, but leauing theyr owne waye torned theyr feete into thy vineyard, that they myght plucke her grapes &amp; take awaye her frutes: not ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritual, but temporal frutes. What is it, that thou telleſt me? This I ſaye, o Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. The riche robbes of this worlde wal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waye of theyr ſinnes, ſeking by ryght &amp; wronge for riches, dignytes promotions &amp; pleaſures of this worlde hath gon aſyde out of theyr waye. They ceaſed to folowe theſe worldely goodes, for ſuche ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; honour did they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour nomore: they turned themſelfe to thy vineyarde, to eccleſiaſtical auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to the ryches of the churche: that wal which did put backe the vnworthie is broken downe &amp; deſtroyed, yea &amp; they haue entred in that paſſeth by their ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne waye, &amp; haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaye the frutes.
<pb facs="tcp:26464:19"/>What ſayeſt thou? This, I meane: To daye in the commen route of men, &amp; to morowe in the roume of a Biſhop:</p>
            <p>To daye in a tolebothe, &amp; to morow a chanon in the quier: To daye a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, &amp; to morow a preſte. They paſſed by theyr owne waye, &amp; wente a ſyde to thy vineyarde: not to the entente to til it for the, but to gather the grapes ther of for themſelfe. This alſo I ſpeake with teares: Ther haue entered in euil ſpyrites, and fyue naughty men (that is to ſaye) the hedde, &amp; the membres: &amp; plucking the goſtely frutes of this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyarde haue caſte them forthe, trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de them vnder feete, hidde them, deſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the tyllars and workers haue they ſtryke with the ſwerde, &amp; throwne them out of the vineyarde: the beſte braunches haue they cutte of: fynally with miſcheuous perſwaſyons, threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teninges, perſecutyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and euyl enſam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples they go aboute to bring to nought what ſo euer goodnes is founde in the vineiarde. Wherfore then haſte thou, Lorde, deſtroyed the wal of it?</p>
            <p>What profyte, what frute therof enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth? For bicauſe of that doth euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that paſſeth by the waye pull the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of yt. But wolde God onely men,
<pb facs="tcp:26464:19"/>or wycked ſpyrites goyng by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye did gather the grapes of it, and not alſo very beaſtes did entre in to it. But lo a naughty beaſte hath gone in to it, &amp; hath deſtroyed it euen from the rote.</p>
            <q>A Boore out of the woode hath broken the bandes of it: and a ſingular wilde beaſte hath deuoured it.</q>
            <p>This boore is a ſwyn, a fylthie ſwyn, a proud ſwyn, a cruel ſwyn: not tamed at home, but wilde out of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wood: an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clarke, a lecherous preſte, whiche is no man, but a beaſte, but an vncle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſwyn: he aprocheth to thy altar, he hath layn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole nyght in his beaſtly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, indirt, in do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mornyng pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſumeth to touche thy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. This proude ſwyne can not be tamed, wil not be corrected, &amp; letteth ſcorn to hear y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes of trouthe: he ſpeaketh arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, he aryſeth agaynſt who ſo rebuketh hym, he byteth, he teareth fierſly, he ſpa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth no wordes, he curſeth, he blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in the deſpite of God. He is a hog<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, he is cruel, he is a beaſte, not a man: he perſecuteth men: he is no domeſtical nor of the houſeholde, no not ſo moche as newly grafted in: he commeth not out of the Lordes houſe, but from the
<pb facs="tcp:26464:20"/>woode, from the company of beaſtes, from the multitude of wylde beaſtes, from the wilderneſſe of ſynners. He knoweth not God, he is ignoraunte in the ſacramentes, he vnderſtandeth not his owne offyce: he onely loueth dyrth, he embraceth donge, he is delyted with bloode. Why then what hathe this boo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re done o Lorde God? He hath rooted vp thy vineyarde, he hath put it out of thy bondes, out of thy preceptes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandementes, out of thy inſtructyons &amp; teachinges of the primatiue fathers, out of thy lawes hath he ſet it: he hath replenyſhed it with dirthe and do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, with exceſſiue pleaſures and vnclea nelynes, with gluttonie &amp; dronckardye. The tyllars hath he ſlayne, the yonge children hath he killed, the women hath he deſloured, the braunches hath he dra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the grounde, the vynes hath he plucked vp by the roote, &amp; hath torne al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to gyther wyth his tethe: with his pride hath he trode the trees vnder his feete, and caſte them forthe of the vineyarde. This boore comming out of the woode hath broken the bondes of it, and a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulare wilde beaſte hath deuoured it. Lo what pryde is here? He wil nedes be ſingular, he wil haue no ſuperior, he
<pb facs="tcp:26464:20"/>wil haue no peas, he loketh not to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue felowes, but ſeruauntes &amp; ſubiectes: he coueteth to poſſeſſe al ſingularly, he ſeketh euermore to aſcende, he is dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a ſingularite, he regardeth not Chriſte his charyte: he wil not be a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtre, nor ſheparde, nor father, nor mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, nor partaker of tribulacyon, nor euery mannes ſeruaunte to the enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te for to winne euery man: but a lorde, but a wolfe, but a cruel &amp; a ſturdye ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to deſtroye the vineyarde, to plucke vp the rootes, vtterly to waſte it, holly to eate it, &amp; bring it to noughte. Is not alſo this wilde boore and ſyngulare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſte an euil Prince, a proude tyraunte, al togyther vncleane, al togyther cruel? Whiche commeth out of the wilde woo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of beaſtes, from miniſters lyke him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>felfe, fylthye, ryottous, arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, cruel that ar beaſtes and no men. Whiche hateth the worſhypping of God, bany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth holy men out of the cyte, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the goode, punyſheth the wyſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſteth and can not abyde the trouthe, reioyceth in lyes, is delyted with flate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring tales, driueth awaye concorde, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth debate, breaketh matrimonie, putteth vertues to exyle, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, chaſeth awaye chaſtyte, enhaunſeth
<pb facs="tcp:26464:21"/>vngracious perſones, fynally cauſeth al noughtynes to be at the ful flynge. He hath burſte the bandes of the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde, for that he hath ſtande by euery waye that is not good, &amp; hath not beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the contrary trade to vertue &amp; hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtye. Is not this boore percaſe &amp; ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar wilde beaſte alſo the deuil? A fowle ſpyrite, a cruel mankyller, puffed vp with pryde, that ſayde: Into heuen wil I clyme, aboue the ſterres of the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wil I exalte my ſcate, I wil be ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnto the hyeſt. He alſo hath fed de v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the vineyarde, hath eaten the brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, hath ſwalowed the vines &amp; hath incorporat it wyth hymſelfe: he is beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head of myſchief, &amp; they his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres: and Chriſte his vineyarde, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comme the deuylls vineyard, for that a ſyngular wyld beaſt hath deuoured it, Alas alas alas Lorde God, wher is the vineyarde whiche thou diddeſt tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te out of Egypte, out of which thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt caſte the Heathen, which thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſet with thyne owne handes, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe iourney thou diddeſt guyde, which repleniſhed the earthe with vertues, whoſe ſhadow couered the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taynes, and the vines, &amp; the cedre trees of God, whiche did ſtretche oute her braunches
<pb facs="tcp:26464:21"/>eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſee, &amp; her ſpredding boughes vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riuer. Where bene her vertues? where are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gyftes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſte? whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ar the graces frely beſtowed? where is her loue? where is her hope? where is her fayth? Arte not thou God, with whome ther is no chaunge? Arte not thou he, that is to ſaye. God which did deſt worke mercy with our fathers? Ar not we the workemnaſhyp of thy han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des? Doth not Chriſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinew for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more? Haſte not thou alſo ſuffred for vs? Haſte thou forgotten vs o Lorde? Thou Lorde arte our father, and Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham knewe vs not, nor yet Iſrael.</p>
            <p>Thou Lorde arte our father, and our re demer, thy name hath bene from the be gynnyng. Wherfore then haſte thou turned thy face from vs? We haue ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, we haue done amyſſe, we haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted naughtynes. Lorde deale not with vs after our ſynnes, nother re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde vs according to our iniquyties. Lorde remembre not our olde fautes, lette thy mercye preuente vs anonne, for we ar very nedy &amp; poore. No, nor yet our fathers wer founde ryghteous: but ſynners, worſhippers of idoles, murderers, curſers, couetous, proude &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:26464:22"/>hye mindes not obedient to theyr pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, folyſh, &amp; blaſphemyng thy name.</p>
            <p>Yet haſte thou delte with them euen ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to thy greate mercye. For they poſſeded not the earthe in theyr ſwerde, nether theyr owne powre ſaued them: but thy ryght hande, &amp; thy powre, &amp; the lyghtenyng of thy countenaunce, bicau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe thou werte pleaſed in them. Go to therfore, &amp; deale with vs after thy grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te mercy, &amp; turne not awaye thy face from vs.</p>
            <q>God of myghte be thou turned, loke backe from heuen and beholde, &amp; viſit this vinciarde.</q>
            <p>God of powers that arte a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re acte, a power infynyte, the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of powers, gouerning al thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, doyng al thynges, quickening al thinges, creating the poures of al thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, ges, gyuyng them ſtrength, drawing them to theyr worke, goyng afore them turne vs (o Lorde) vnto the, &amp; we ſhal be turned: go thou before vs, drawe vs after the, gyue ſtrength to our ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and make vs lyuely. Why doeſt thou not loke vpon vs? Why haſte thou turned thy backe? Shewe vs thy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenaunce.
<pb facs="tcp:26464:22"/>Be turned God of poures vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs, and then ſhal we be turned vnto the. For to be conuerted vnto the, to thynke vpon the, to loue the, it is thy gyfte. Loke backe from heuen: for thou arte gone farre henſe, thou haſte aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded euen vp in to heauen: thou arte de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from vs, yet loke vpon vs from heuen, although thou wilte not comme doune to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, although our ſynnes doth otherwyſe deſerue: regarde vs, ſende vs thy lyght from aboue, from the deſerte of compaſſions, from the Chriſte, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the place where as thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſayntes prayeth for vs. See how we ar made deſolate &amp; comfortles, beholde &amp; take pyte vpon our ſhame and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che: our herytage is traunſlated vnto ſtraungers, our houſes vnto forynars. Where is Hieruſalem? Where is the holy lande, wherin thou diddeſt worke ſo many myracles? Where is thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue? Ar thy not in the handes of infy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels? Beholde Lorde with the eyes of thy mercye the hole worlde, &amp; the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe therof: not the fulneſſe of graces, but plentyeth of ſynnes, plentieth of ignoraunce, plentieth of wretchednes. Beholde thy vineyarde, thy churche, the common welthe, thy Chriſtian people,
<pb facs="tcp:26464:23"/>beholde and haue pyte vpon them. And viſyt this vineyarde. For yet to hath it rootes, yet ther lyueth ſome brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches: it beganne from the begynnyng of the worlde, &amp; neuer fayled, nor neuer ſhal fayle. For thou haſte promyſed: Lo with you am I al dayes euen vnto the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ende. Then wel maye it be dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed, but vtterly fayle it can not.</p>
            <p>Now this vineyarde is the ſelfe ſame, that thou diddeſt plante. Ther is one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit, one fayth, one baptime or fulleni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, one God &amp; Lorde of all, which is al to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther in al thinges. Viſyte therfore this vineyarde, for thy viſitatyon ſhal kepe her ſpyryte: viſyte herwith thy gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, with thy preſence, with thy holy ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite. Viſyte it alſo with thy wande, and with thy ſtaffe. For thy wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; thy ſtaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe ſhal comforte it. Viſyte it with a ſcour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, that ſhe may be chaſtiſed and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: for the ſeaſon of pluckyng awaye thinges ſuperfluous wil comme. Thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we forthe the ſtones, make fagottes of the wythered braunches and drie ſticks to be burned. Rayſe her vp, cutte of the refuſe, ſet vnder ſtayes &amp; proppes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the grounde ranke &amp; ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful, buylde the wal, &amp; vyſyte this vineyarde, lyke as thou haſte al redy viſyted the earth,
<pb facs="tcp:26464:23"/>and inebryate it. Viſyt her, I ſaye:</p>
            <q>And make her parfecte, whome thy ryght hande hath planted, and that v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſonne of man whome thou ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte made ſtronge for thyſelf.</q>
            <p>Do not onely viſyt her, but alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke her parfecte. For ſhe is very vnpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte. She wolde luye wel, but ſhe nolde ſuffre euil. She hath enſamples ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her eyes, ſhe hath the Prophetes, the Apoſtles, the Martyres, &amp; al the ſain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of God: yea ſhe hath the very onely begotten ſonne: them wolde ſhe folowe, wel wolde ſhe do for to get theyr glory, but aduerſytes wold ſhe not abyde. She is very vnparfyte. Make her parfecte, o Lorde: Sende for the thy ſpirite, and then ſhal ſhe be made parfecte. Peter be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the comming of the holy goſte ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de: yea if I muſte nedes be put to death w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the, I will not denye the. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe for as moche as he was vnparfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, at the voyce of one poore mayde he de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyed the Chriſte. The holy Goſte cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, &amp; fulfylled him with grace: &amp; then he feared not kynges of the earth, for that thou madeſt hym parfecte: tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did he bring forthe frute, than did he turne
<pb facs="tcp:26464:24"/>an exceding ſorte of people to the fayth, than did he buylde churches and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for the holy goſte to dwel in.</p>
            <p>Wherfore make her parfect: and then wil ſhe bryng forth frute, and wil ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che out her braunches thorough y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. For yet is ſhe afrayde, yet dare ſhe not ſpeake, yet ſhe feareth prynces &amp; ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers. Make her parfecte, whome thy ryght hande hath planted: not her, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me thy lefte hande hath pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted. For ther ar ſome Chriſtianes, as certayne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes by name, not in very dede: vnto whome thou haſte gyuen the ryches of this worlde, and multiplyed theyr tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral goodes, but of thy ſpiritual Goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des haue they none. Theſe therfore ar the vineyard, which thy lefte hande hath planted. I deſyre the not to encreaſe this vineyarde, or to make it parfecte: but that whiche thy ryght ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hath planted, which beareth braunches (that is to ſaye) the faythful, to whome thou haſt gyuen thy grace, and thy goſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly gyftes: whych ar thyne elected. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge whome euery one ſayeth: His lefte hande vnder my hedde, and hys ryght hande ſhal embrace me. Make therfore this vineyarde parfecte, make her parfecte (I ſaye) vpon the ſonne of
<pb facs="tcp:26464:24"/>man, whome thou haſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed for thy ſelfe. Who is this ſonne of man? For we ar the ſonnes of men, bicauſe we haue a father &amp; a mother here in the worlde. But Chriſte is the ſonne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is the ſonne of a mayde: which in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath a father w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out a mother, &amp; in earthe a mother without a father. This ſonne of man therfore haſte thou made ſtedfaſte in the hartes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne: &amp; haſte alſo confirmed hym for thyſelfe (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is) to thy honour &amp; glory. The lande of Iewrye fought agaynſt hym, and thou madeſt hym ſure vnto the: tyrauntes hath foughte agaynſte hym, &amp; thou ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt hym ſure vnto the: heretykes hath foughte agaynſt hym, and thou madeſt hym ſure vnto the: Philoſophers, logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, &amp; the wyſe me of this worlde hath foughte agaynſte hym, and thou made hym ſure vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>: falſe bretherne hath foughte agaynſt hym, and thou madeſt hym ſure vnto the: the deuyl, &amp; the hole worlde foughte agaynſt hym, &amp; preuay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not, but thou haſte made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faſte &amp; ſure in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes hartes to thy honour &amp; glory. Therfore make parfecte this vineyard vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe by fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the &amp; loue planted &amp; rooted vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte maye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me to parfectneſſe, &amp; out of that
<pb facs="tcp:26464:25"/>redde earthe, out of that entyer zeale of Chriſte his charyte, out of the merites of his paſſyon maye bringe forthe very good wyne rauyſhyng mannes har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Albeit for that ſhe is vnparfecte, for that ſhe is fallen, for that the worlde is agaynſt her, this ſemeth vnpoſſible in the eyes of menne: yet Lorde nothyng is impoſſible, nor nothyng harde vnto the. Thou openeſt thy hande, &amp; fylleſt euery lyuely creature with bleſſing. Al thynges loketh that thou ſhouldeſt gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue them food in ſeaſon. When thou gyueſt them, they wil gather: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou openeſt thy hand, al thinges ſhal be fyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led with goodneſſe. But whan thou tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſt awaye thy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenaunce, they ſhal be troubled: thou ſhalte take awaye theyr ſpirite, and they ſhal faynte, and be retourned into theyr duſte. How mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che more then, whan thou rebukeſt, ſhal al ſtoppes be taken awaye, and al deſtroyers be deſtroyed?</p>
            <q>They kyndled with fyre, and dygged vp at the rebuke of thy countenaunce ſhal peryſh.</q>
            <p>For the kindled and halfe burned ſtycks, and vynes dygged vp, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruteful
<pb facs="tcp:26464:25"/>trees diſparſed thorough the vineyarde, &amp; the younge braunches cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, doth marre the lyuyng vynes &amp; letteth them to bringe forthe frute.</p>
            <p>Them therfore kindled and dygged vp rebuke with thy countenaunce, with that countenaunce wherof is ſpoken: But the Lordes countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is ouer al euil doers: and forthwith the vnfrute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful trees ſhal periſh: they (I meane) which nether entereth themſelfe in to the kingdome of heauen, nor yet ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret other to enter. So that theſe kinled trees ar vncleane ſynners, fyred with the heate of carnal luſte, &amp; turned in to coles: walking in darkeneſſe, &amp; kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing not whyther they go. For the fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hath ſytte ouer them, &amp; they haue not ſoene thy ſonne. This woode kindled with fyre ar couetouſe men &amp; gredy in the deſyre of monye, inflamed with the inordinat fyre of auaryce, which neuer ſayeth ynough ynough, or whoe whoe. Theſe trees kindled with fyre are men prowde, deſyrons of honour, and enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men: which burneth lyke as fyre brandes, &amp; ar incended with couetyng of al thinges. This fyre hath waſted al vertues, hath rayſed al wanton luſtes, is the cauſe of al vngraciouſnes. For
<pb facs="tcp:26464:26"/>pryde is the foundacion of al naughty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and vehement deſyre of wilful ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite is the roote of al vnhappynes: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for the turning awaye from God, thys for the turning vnto creatures. Now who ar the trees dygged vp. but Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites nohter hote nor colde, which out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly certeſſe ſemeth not to be burned with the fyre of luſte, or pryde, or coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe: yet inwardely ar they drye bicauſe they ar dygged vp, they haue no rootes in the earth of the lyung trees, in the charite of Chriſte, in the grace of God. Wherfor euen as a tree, if it hath rootes in the earth, it bryngeth forth frutes at the heate of the ſunne: but if it hath no rootes in the earth, but in the ayer, it wythereth awaye at the heate of the ſunne. Semblably a man if he hath the rootes of fayth and loue in Chriſte, comyng to the auitre, to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes of the churche and godly du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyes, to hear Goddes worde, to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſcriptures, to prayer: bringeth forth maruelous and wonderful frute and profyte. But if his onely ſtudye be for thynges apparteynyng to his owne ſelfe, and is rooted in his owne loue, in the ayre, in the ſpyrite of arrogance: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye about what ſo euer he goeth he
<pb facs="tcp:26464:26"/>wythereth more and more, and is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de worſe and worſe. Hypocrytes therfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ar trees dygged vp, ar drye trees, ar fyrewoode: but certeſſe the very trees that ar dygged vp bene alſo kindled, &amp; the trees kindled ar alſo as the trees dygged vp. For manyfeſt and open ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ar dygged vp, and plucked awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye, and rooted out from the grace of God: and thoſe Hypocrytes ar kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the fyre of the loue of them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, of pryde, of ambytyon, of couetyſe, of pryuye or ſecrete luſte or pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Thus al theyſe Lorde God dyſparſed thorough the vineyarde, and heaped to gyther wil not ſuffre it to bring for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the frutes: bicauſe the yonglynges and ſimple folke ar ceduced and ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen with theyr euil enſamples and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Rebuke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore rebuke them roughly, for that they ar ſtyffe-necked: rebuke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ſwerde, peſtylence, and hongre. Thoroughe the reprofe of thy countenaunce ſhal they peryſh, and ſhal be caſte out of the vineyarde: the braunches ſhal be lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp, other vynes ſhal be put therto: they ſhal growe and fructyfye: they ſhal extend theyr ofſpryng euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſee, and ſhal reache vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:26464:27"/>ryuer. Why ſleapeſt thou Lorde? Aryſe Lorde, and</p>
            <q>Let thy power be ſhewed vpon the man of thy ryghte hande, and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſonne of man whome thou haſte ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſure for thyne owne ſelfe.</q>
            <p>Comme Lorde, do not thou tarye. O God gyue thy iudgement to the Kinge, and thy iuſtyce to the Kynges ſonne. For he is the man of thy ryght hande, which ſytteth at thy ryght han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. But which is thy ryght hande? For thou arte inuiſyble and with out any body. Where is then thy ryght, or thy lefte hande? Thy glory is thy ryght ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Namely therfore of Chriſte was it ſpoken, that he ſytteth at thy ryght han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, bicauſe he reioyſeth in better felicite aboue al domynyon, and power, and ſtrength, and aboue euery name that is recyted not onely in this worlde, but alſo in the worlde to comme. And what is thy hande, but thy power? If thou then haſte a ryght ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, why haſte thou not lykewyſſe a lefte hand? For power haſte thou to puniſh, and to gloryfye. For the Lorde doth quicken and morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye, doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uey to hel and recarye, doth
<pb facs="tcp:26464:27"/>bring lowe and exalte. Powre ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to puniſh is thy lefte hande, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to gloryfye is thy ryght hande. Let thy hande therfore, let thy powre com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vpon thy man of the right hande. How ſo? Hath not he had powre gyuen hym from the begynnyng? For euen he ſayde to his dyſcyples. Al powre in heauen and in earth is gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me. How canſt thou then ſaye: let thy han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de comme vpon the man of the ryght hande? Gyuen hym it is, but it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not: bring to paſſe therfore that it maye appeare. Beaſtely &amp; carnal men doth perceyue &amp; ſee how that thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes ar mocked, deſpyſed, ſclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and ar euermore in trouble and aduerſyte, and then do they ſaye.</p>
            <p>Fayth is not true, purueyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God is ther none, deceyued ar the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and ſo doe they blaſpheme thy na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me. To be breue they ſee proude men, vnryghteous, couetous, blaſphemers, lecherous, and vngracious men to go forwarde, &amp; to haue no aduerſe chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce: ſo that they ſaye. Other ther is no God, or elles he doth not regarde mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tal mennes matters, other els he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſte and vnequal. Thou then haſte powre, and doſte contynually exercyſe
<pb facs="tcp:26464:28"/>thy iudgementes, but they do not apea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re alwaye, and for that cauſe doth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeake in thy deſpite and reproche. Let thy hande therfore be made to apeare vpon the man of thy right hande.</p>
            <p>Graunte hym iudgement that maye apeare. Bidde hym exercyſe the power that he hath in the ſyght of menne.</p>
            <p>For thou haſte ordeyned hym iudge of the quicke and the deade. Let thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de therfore comme vpon hym. Which hande? the righte, or the lefte hande? Let thy lefte, and alſo the ryght hand comme vpon hym: The lefte vpon the euil, the ryght hande vpon the good. Let thy iudgement apeare, and let thy mercye apeare, that men maye leaue of curſynge and blaſphemynge. Dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thy lefte hande is weaker than the ryght, bycauſe thou doſte execute iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement with mercye, and art lothe for to puniſhe. But thy ryght hand is ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, for that thou art a large and a lybe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ral gyuer. Thou openeſt thy hande, euen thy ryght ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, and fylleſt euery lyuing creature w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bleſſing. Let it come therfore vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy ryght ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Let thy left ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de be to puniſh the wicked, that they maye be ſcourged, and ſo conuerted. And if they wil not be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto the, that they maye be cleane
<pb facs="tcp:26464:28"/>putte out of thy vineyarde, and maye be puniſhed in the fyre of hel for euer. For why do they occupye the earth in vayne? But let thy ryght hand be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the man of thy ryght hande to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neforte thy faythful, that in a plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bleſſing they maye be fylled with the grace of the holy goſte, that the wal of the vineyarde maye be buylded vp to holde out them that paſſeth by the waye: and not to ſuffre the boore of the woode, and a ſyngular wylde beaſte to entre in: to the entente that the vinebraunches maye growe and bring forth frute. Yea is it not (trowe ye) profytable, that both thy handes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be vpon the man of thy ryght han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de for thy faythful? Yes vndoutedly.</p>
            <p>For thy lefte hande, thy hande holding the ſcourge, thy hande that is wonte to ſtryke wil cauſe them to tary at the ryght hande. For the rodde in the ſcho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les kepeth the chylde in awe, the wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de maketh hym to lerne. For as yet are we yong chyldren: bicauſe as longe as we ar in thys mortal lyffe, we ar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes, we had nede of the rodde, we ar fedde wyth mylke. But when that ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, whyche is parfecte, the preper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes of a yonglyng ſhal we laye apart
<pb facs="tcp:26464:29"/>for al togyther: &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal the ſcourge leaue of. Thy ſcourge therfore is good and holſome, let thy ſcourge therfore comme, let it comme ſoone, let the pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re quickly comme vpon the ſonne of thy ryght hande: that the goode maye be purged, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſt maye be made parfe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cte, that the euil maye be expelled, that the deſtroyers of the vineyarde maye peryſh. And vpon the ſonne of man let the vinebraunches be grafted, whom thou haſt made ſure to thy ſelf, whome thou haſte confyrmed in the congregacion to thy honour. For yet is he not hollye gone fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the churche. Yet haſte thou many ſeruauntes, alga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes they be pryuye and ſecret, in whoſe hartes thou haſte confirmed thy Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte to thy glorye: and let them, when as the deſtroyers of the vineyarde ar dry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen out, go forth to theyr worke euen vntyll nyght. Comme therfore, o Lord, &amp; couple vs to thy tyllars, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me thou haſte prepared vnto thy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. We ar thy ſeruauntes.</p>
            <q>And we do not departe from thee: thou ſhalt quicken vs and vpon thy name wyll we call.</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:26464:29"/>
            <p>We can not be withoute the. For in the haue we our lyuing, our mouyng, and our beyng. And therfore do not we departe from the, ſeyng that thou haſte the wordes of euerlaſting lyffe. To whom ſhal we go? Ther is no God beſyd the Lorde. For who hath worked ſuch wonderful maruayles, as thou haſte done? Al thynges that thou lyſted haſte thou made in heauen &amp; in earth, in the ſee and in al places be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo depe or bottomleſſe. Although the worlde crie out, men grudge, and the wicked perſecute vs: although the elementes euery one make inſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yea although hel wolde breake lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe and be reyſed agaynſt vs: yet depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te we not from the, no creature can ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtre vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loue of God, which is in Chriſte Ieſus our Lorde. We do not truſte in our owne ſtrenght, we go not forth in our owne vertues: but thou ſhalt make vslyuely. Plenteouſly ſhalte thou graunte vs thy grace, thou ſhalt gyue vs vertues, in our trouble ſhalte thou ſende vs a ſpecyal ayde wherby we ſhal be prouoked to the fer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uentneſſe of charyte. And vpon thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me wil we cal. Thy name is thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: For none is goode, but God alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.
<pb facs="tcp:26464:30"/>Thou alone therfore art goode, to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alone this name doth wel accorde. So then thy name (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter of thy name, the thyng ſygnifyed by thy name: thy goodneſſe (I meane) and thy mercy ſhal we cal vpon, that it ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ye helpe vs and ſocoure vs. Orels ſure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to cal vpon thy name is to frame and facyon in our mynde a conceyte or apprehenſyon of thy goodneſſe: for it is a name onely conceyued in myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de: ſo that the conceyuing of thy goode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is thy name. Not euery co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyt or thoucht is thy name, which called vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaueth a man, as it is written: Who ſo euer calleth vpon the name of the Lorde, ſhal be ſaffe: but the concey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of thy goodnes, which thorough fayeth braſteth forth in to loue, and that by the gyfte of grace farre beyond the courſe of nature: this, I ſaye, is thy name. What is it then to cal vpon thy name, but inwardlye by fayth to conceyue thy goodeneſſe, and to loue it aboue al thinges. For a name is a voyce ſumwhat betokenyng. What is it then to cal vpon any mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, but to pronounce a voyce that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokeneth hym? So that to cal vpon the name of God with our lyppes and
<pb facs="tcp:26464:30"/>tounge, is to bryng forth a voyce that ſygnifieth hym. Lykewyſe where ther is alſo a name onely compryſed in mynd and vnderſtandyng: to cal vpon thy name with our hart and mynde, is to frame a thought or conceyte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentyng and layeng the before our eyes. Yet not euery manner thynking of the is ynough, but that apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of thee ſaueth: which is formed by the vertue of fayth, that worketh by loue. Wherfore we wil cal vpon thy name w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our hert, we wil cal wyth our lippes and tunge: that from thy bounteouſnes called vpon the ayde maye deſcende vnto vs wel diſpoſed and prepared, which haue thorough thy grace inwardly receyued thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Gyue vs therfore ſtrenght and vertue, wherby al earthly deſyre vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly layed awaye we maye be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto the euen with al our very harte, that in our troubles we fayle not for febleneſſe.</p>
            <q>God of myght conuerte vs, and ſhewe thy face, and we ſhal be ſaffe,</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:26464:31"/>
            <p>Certeſſe thou arte God of myght, whiche haſte choſen the vyle &amp; weake thynges of the world, &amp; therwyth haſt confounded all ſtoute &amp; ſtronge thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. For what is weaker the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe? What is more folyſh? What is more curſed? Lo thorough thy infynyte pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re &amp; myghte thys greteſt infirmyte is made for vs the greteſt ſtrenght &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fence. This moſt vnſkylful folyſhnes is made for menne moſte profounds wyſdome. This hygh &amp; extreme cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng is made for vs an heuenly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng &amp; moſte parfecte iuſtyce. O the wonderfull depeneſſe of the ryches of God his myght, &amp; his wyſdome, &amp; his bonteouſnes. For that which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ake thyng of God, is ſtronger tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is the folyſh thyng of God, is wyſer than men. Make vs (o Lorde) to vnderſtande thys thy infynyte pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re thy vnſearchable wyſdome, thy in eſtymable goodneſſe: that we maye knowe ther is no other God beſyde the Lorde, and maye be turned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the. Conuerte vs God of myght, &amp; ſhewe thy countenaunce. Shewe thy Chriſte, thy crucyfied: by whome we haue knowne thy powre, thy wyſdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and thy bonyte. What God hath
<pb facs="tcp:26464:31"/>at any tyme don ſuch thynges, as hath thy ſonne our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cified for vs? He conquered the hole worlde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſwerde, he hath throwen downe al the other Goddes, tyraun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes hath he deſtroyed, euery where in heuen &amp; in earth hath he triumphed for vaynquiſſyng his enemys, he hath lyghtened the worlde by his croſſe, he hath taughte how to lyue wel, he hath gyuen and preſcrybed the doctryne or waye to lyue verteouſly, ſo as no bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter can be ymagyned. He hath drawne to his loue al kyndes of men, which re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nouncyng &amp; leauyng golde, ſyluer, &amp; al the vanytes of thys worlde, yea and themſelues to: hath alſo gladly for hys ſake and cherefully ſuffered kindes of tormentryes moſte ſpytefully deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed euen tyl they wer martyred and cruelly done to death.</p>
            <p>Who euer herde of ſuch thynges? Or who hath ſeene the lyke? In very dede Lorde Ieſus, thou arte a greate God, the ſonne of the hyeſt God, the kynge of glory, the God of myght: and ther is no God but thou Lorde, which with the father and holy goſte arte one God bleſſed aboue al thinges. Shewe vs therfore thy face. In thy ſyghte was
<pb facs="tcp:26464:32"/>the earth moued, in the ſyghte, of the God of Iacob: which turned a ſtonne in to a ſtandyng poole, and a rocke in to ſprynges of waters. Lorde ſhewe thy face, and we ſhal be ſaffe. For our fathers alſo were made ſaffe, bicauſe thou diddeſt ſhewe them thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, wherfore they prayſe the and ſaye: Not vnto vs Lorde, not vnto vs Lorde, not vnto vs, but vnto thy name gyue the glory, for thy mercye and thy trouthes ſake. Shewe thy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce therfore o Lorde, that the reiected or wicked maye peryſh, for as much as death ſhal go before thy face. Shewe thy countenaunce that thyne elected or choſen maye ſerue the in loue: and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal we be ſaffe and whole, then ſhal the worlde be renewed and adorned with vertues and with thy grace. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal the goode be gladde and reioyce ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cedyngly, then ſhal thy people dwel in peas, and continually daye and nyght gyue prayſe vnto the. Which with thy ſonne, and the holy goſte lyueſt and reygneſt bleſſed God for euer and euer worlde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26464:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
